# Rick Farouni | Curriculum Vitae

McGill University - Génome Québec Innovation Centre

✓ rfarouni@gmail.com • ♦ http://rfarouni.github.io/

I am an applied statistician/computational biologist working on the statistical modeling and analysis of genomics, transcriptomics, epigenomics, and CRISPR genome editing data. On the statistics side, my expertise lies in probabilistic, Bayesian, and latent variable modeling. On the computational biology side, my expertise is mainly confined to the biology of gene regulation and the analysis of experimental data generated in this area. Currently, I am a post-doctoral researcher in computational biology working on the application of Bayesian statistics and machine learning to single-cell transcriptomics data. I received a PhD in Quantitative Psychology (statistics applied to modeling psychological and neuroimaging data), a masters degree in Mathematical Statistics, and a masters degree in Psychometrics from the Ohio State University.

# **Experience**

#### Postdoctoral Researcher

McGill University-Génome Québec Innovation Centre

Research Lab of Dr. Najafabadi, Department of Human Genetics

Montreal, Canada 06/2018-Present

Massachusetts General Hospital-Harvard Medical School

Research Lab of Dr. Pinello, Molecular Pathology Unit

Massachusetts, USA 06/2017-05/2018

- The Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard (Affiliated Member)

Research Intern

Department of Biomedical Informatics Summer Internship Program

Research Lab of Dr. Ewy Mathè, The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA 05/2016-08/2016

#### University Teaching Assistant.

**The Ohio State University**Graduate Teaching Associate (Statistics)

Ohio, USA 2013-2017

Served as a Teaching Assistant for three courses:

- Repeated Measures Models
- Covariance Structure Models
- Data Analysis in Psychology

# **Education**

#### Academic Qualifications

#### PhD in Quantitative Psychology (i.e. Applied Statistics)

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2015-2017

Dissertation Topic: 'Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States'

#### Master of Science in Statistics

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2012-2015

## Master's Degree in Psychometrics

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2012-2014

Thesis Project: 'Latent Variable Modeling of Categorical Item Responses in a Hierarchical Bayesian Framework'

#### Bachelor's Degree in Psychology

Pennsylvania, USA

The Pennsylvania State University

2011-2012

## **Publications**

#### Journal Papers (first author/co-author)

- o Clement, K.†, **Farouni, R.**†, Bauer, D. E., and Pinello, L. (2018). Design and analysis of unique molecular identifiers for deep amplicon sequencing. **Bioinformatics**. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty264. Preprint available at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2018/03/23/288118.full.pdf
- o Pinello, L.<sup>†</sup>, **Farouni, R.**<sup>†</sup>, and Yuan, G-C. (2018). Haystack: systematic analysis of the variation of epigenetic states and cell-type specific regulatory elements. *Bioinformatics*. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty031. Preprint available at https://doi.org/10.101/199067
- o Baskin, E.<sup>†</sup>, **Farouni, R.**<sup>†</sup>, and Mathè, E. (2017). ALTRE: workflow for defining ALTered Regulatory Elements using chromatin accessibility data. *Bioinformatics*. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btx386. Preprint available at http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/10/14/080564.full.pdf+html

## Journal Papers (middle author).....

- Seruggia, D., Oti, M., Tripathi, P., Canver, M.C., Leblanc, L. Giammartino, L., Nefzger, C.M., Yang Sun, Y.B., Farouni, R., Polo, J.M., Pinello, L., Apostolou, E., Kim, J., Orkin, S.H., and Das, P.P. (2019). TAF5L/TAF6L maintains self-renewal of embryonic stem cells via MYC regulatory network. *Molecular Cell*. (accepted)
- o Clement K., Rees H., Canver, M.C., Gehrke J. M., **Farouni, R.**, Hsu, J.Y., Cole, M., Liu D.R., Joung J.K., Bauer, D.E., Pinello, L. (2019). CRISPResso2 provides accurate and rapid genome editing sequence analysis. *Nature Biotechnology*.

 Hsu, J. Y., Fulco, C.P., Cole, M., Canver, M.C., Pellin D., Sher, F, Farouni, R., Clement K., Biasco L., Engreitz, J.M., Lander, E.S., Joung J.K., Bauer, D.E., Pinello, L. (2018). CRISPR-SURF: Exploratory and interactive software for analyzing CRISPR-based tiling screens. *Nature Methods*.

## Consortium Journal Papers (contributor).....

o Grüning, B., Dale, R., Sjödin, A., Rowe, J., Chapman, B. A., Tomkins-Tinch, C. H., The Bioconda Team, and Köster, J.(2018) Bioconda: A sustainable and comprehensive software distribution for the life sciences. *Nature Methods*. (Bioconda team member contributor, ranked 94 in the consortium author list). Preprint available at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/10/27/207092.

Preprints.....

Farouni, R. (2017). A Contemporary Overview of Probabilistic Latent Variable Models. arXiv preprint. Preprint available at https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.08137

#### Dissertation and Thesis

- Farouni, R. (2017). Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States. *PhD Dissertation*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send\_file?accession=osu1492189894812539&disposition=inline
- o Farouni, R. (2014). Latent Variable Models of Categorical Responses in the Bayesian and Frequentist Frameworks. *Masters Thesis*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send\_file?accession=osu1412374136&disposition=inline

## Conference Presentations

## Joint Statistical Meetings

Seattle

O Poster Presentation 2015

**Poster Title**: Across-Subject Predictive Modeling of fMRI BOLD Responses to Faces using a sparse Bayesian Group Factor Analysis Model (available at https://rfarouni.github.io/assets/posters/jsm2015.pdf).

## Journal Review Service.....

**Psychometrika** 

Ad Hoc Reviewer 2015

**Psychological Methods** 

O Ad Hoc Reviewer 2016

# **Software Development**

- o Haystack: A Python bioinformatics pipeline for the identification of genomic regions of epigenetic variability across different cell-types, cell-type specific cis-regulatory elements, and their associated transcription factors. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/pinellolab/haystack\_bio.
- o ALTRE: A Workflow for Identifying ALTered Regulatory Elements using Chromatin Accessibility

# **Awards and Fellowships**

	Graduate Student Conference Presentation Award	
0	The Ohio State University	2015
0	The Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences Summer Graduate Fellowship  The Ohio State University	2015
	<b>Project Proposal</b> : 'Decoding the Pixels of the Face Image from the Voxels of fMRI BOLD Activity Patterns'	
0	The Social and Behavioral Sciences Summer Fellowship The Ohio State University	2014
0	University Fellowship The Ohio State University	2012

## **Technical Skill Set**

- Statistics and Machine Learning
  - **Scientific Programming Languages:** Proficient in and comfortable transitioning between *R*, *Python* depending on computing goals. Familiar with *Julia*.
  - Deep Learning Frameworks: Experienced in using Pytorch, Tensorflow, and Keras.
  - Probabilistic Programming Languages: Proficient in Stan, familiar with Edward.
- Bioinformatics Software: Analysis of next generation sequencing data, R's Bioconductor core packages, Bowtie2, bedtools.
- Cluster and High-Performance Computing: Good knowledge of running bioinformatics analysis pipelines on super-computing clusters.
- Web and Software Development Tools: LaTeX, Linux OS, Git, Docker, and Bash. Basic knowledge in website development tools such as HTML, CSS, and Jekyll.

## **Personal Details**

- o Country of Current Residence: Canada
- o Countries of Previous Residence: USA, Russia, Jordan
- o Interests and Hobbies: Theoretical Linguistics, Evolutionary Biology, Experimental Music
- Languages Spoken: English, Arabic, Russian, Spanish (intermediate), French (intermediate)